Smith Family
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Russell, Xanthus, and Mary Smith family papers
1793-1977, bulk 1826-1977
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Smith family (Philadelphia, Pa.)
4.6 linear feet
The Russell, Xanthus, and Mary Smith family papers comprise 4.6 linear feet and are dated 1793-1977, bulk 1826-1977. Correspondence, writings, artwork, financial records, printed material, miscellaneous items and photographs provide documentation of the lives and works of painter, illustrator and poet, Russell Smith, and his son, painter Xanthus Smith, and scattered documentation of the lives of his wife, painter and educator Mary Priscilla Smith, and daughter and painter Mary Russell Smith.
Provenance
The Smith family papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 1978 and 1979 by Franklin R. Smith, a family descendent.
Alternative Forms Available
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 2035-2040, and 2062 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. The arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is partially microfilmed. Use of material not microfilmed requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Russell Smith (1812-1896) was a native of Glasgow, Scotland whose family came to the United States in 1819 and settled near Pittsburgh. The Smith children were educated at home, and Russell showed an early interest in art. His first formal training in portraiture and landscape painting was in Pittsburgh under James Reid Lambdin. Around 1827, Smith began painting backdrops for theaters and within 6 years had achieved a national reputation for his theatrical painting. In 1835 he moved to Philadelphia to paint for the Walnut Street Theater, and soon received commissions to paint for theaters in Boston and Washington. Around this time, he also began writing poetry. Even while engaged in theatrical work, Smith continued to paint landscapes which were exhibited at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts and the Artists' Fund Society of Philadelphia as early as 1834.
Russell Smith married Mary Priscilla Wilson, a flower painter and teacher of French and drawing, in 1838. By the 1840s, in addition to painting landscapes and theatrical backdrops, Smith was advertising his services as an "illustrator for lectures on various branches of natural science painted in distemper." He accompanied the scientific expeditions of geologists William Barton Rogers and Henry Darwin Rogers to Virginia and the Susquehanna and Juniata River valleys of Pennsylvania in 1844 and 1845 as an illustrator. During this period, Smith also traveled extensively in New Hampshire and upstate New York for summer painting expeditions. The Smiths traveled to Europe with their two children in 1851-1852, touring Wales, Scotland, Switzerland, Italy, the Netherlands, London, and Paris. Smith visited major museums and private collections, as well as architectural attractions, making sketches and keeping detailed notes of the trip.
Smith continued painting landscapes well into old age, even though his long out of fashion works were rejected with increasing frequency by the juries of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. He died in 1896.
Born in Milestown, Pennsylvania in 1819, Mary Priscilla Smith (1819-1874) studied at a female seminary in Germantown, Pennsylvania operated by noted educator William Russell (Russell Smith's uncle) in Germantown, Pennsylvania, and at Charles Picot's school in Philadelphia. She eventually became a teacher of French, drawing, and painting at the Picot school, and later taught at a school established by William Russell in Philadelphia.
At her husband's urging, Mary Priscilla Smith, already an accomplished flower painter, began painting figures and landscapes, and participated in exhibitions of the Artists' Fund Society exhibitions. After becoming a mother, she painted very little but taught her children, Xanthus and Mary, to draw and paint. Mary Priscilla Smith died in 1874.
Xanthus Smith (1839-1929) was born in Philadelphia and was educated at home. During the family's European tour of 1851-1852 he saw a wide variety of art and, upon returning home, began painting with enthusiasm. Around 1858 he enrolled in a cast drawing class at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts.
At the start of the Civil War Xanthus Smith enlisted in the Navy, where he served as clerk to the commander of a flagship guarding Port Royal, South Carolina. He began producing detailed drawings of the ships both for official purposes and his own enjoyment. After the war, he continued painting ships and exhibited many of these paintings at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. Further commissions of Civil War subjects followed, and Xanthus Smith was soon recognized as the foremost painter of Civil War naval battle scenes.
In the 1880s, Xanthus Smith began painting European landscapes, probably based on his father's sketches made during their 1851-1852 tour of Europe. By the 1900s, he was concentrating on portraiture and figure subjects, and continued painting well into old age. His final years were spent in an unsuccessful attempt to publish his autobiography, "An Unvarnished Tale." Xanthus Smith died in 1929.
Mary Russell Smith (1842-1878) was born near Jenkintown, Pennsylvania. Her mother provided her with instruction in flower painting and she sketched animals and insects independently. At age fourteen Mary Smith completed her first oil painting and by 1858 had begun compiling a list of her completed pictures. She was encouraged by her parents to pursue a career as a professional artist. From 1859-1869, and in 1876 and 1878, Mary Smith exhibited at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. She also participated in exhibitions at the National Academy of Design in New York, and in the 1876 Centennial Exhibition held in Philadelphia.
From early childhood, Mary Smith enjoyed raising poultry, and chickens became her favorite painting subject. Her paintings of chickens were popular with Philadelphia art collectors, and sought after in England.
Always sickly, Mary Smith died of gastric fever in 1878. At her request, Russell Smith established the Mary Smith Prize, awarded annually by the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, for the best painting exhibited by a woman resident of Philadelphia.
Scope and Content Note
The Russell, Xanthus, and Mary Smith family papers comprise 4.6 linear feet and are dated 1793-1977, bulk 1826-1977. Correspondence, writings, artwork, financial records, printed material, miscellaneous items and photographs provide documentation of the lives and works of painter, illustrator and poet, Russell Smith, and his son, painter Xanthus Smith, and scattered documentation of the lives of his wife, painter and educator Mary Priscilla Smith, and daughter and painter Mary Russell Smith.
Family papers include correspondence, writings, printed material, and miscellaneous items. Correspondence, the bulk of which is comprised of letters to and from Russell and Xanthus Smith, covers both personal and professional matters. Among the correspondents are family, friends, colleagues, and arts organizations. Writings, printed material, and miscellaneous items in this series refer either to the entire Smith family or multiple individuals. Miscellaneous items also concern Horace Binder, father-in-law of Xanthus Smith.
The Russell Smith papers are comprised of biographical information, writings, artwork, and financial records. Biographical information includes some personal documents such as passports and marriage certificates. Among Russell Smith's writings are an autobiography, transcripts of correspondence, and notes. Artwork consists of loose pages and sketch books containing sketches and drawings in pencil, ink, and watercolor. His financial records are cash books recording professional and personal expenses, and receipts and memorabilia from the family's 1851-1852 travels in Europe. The printed material consists of loose clippings and a scrapbook of clippings from Philadelphia newspapers, as well as a small number of exhibition catalogs.
The Xanthus Smith papers consist of biographical information, artwork, financial records, and printed material. Among the writings are his unpublished autobiography, biographies of his father and sister, impressions of the Centennial art exhibition, journals, notes, and poems. Artwork consists of loose sketches in pencil and ink, and sketchbooks containing sketches and finished drawings in pencil and ink, some colored with gouache or watercolor washes. Financial records are cash books recording personal and professional expenses. Printed material includes clippings and a scrapbook.
The Mary Smith papers consist of writings, sketches, and printed material. The papers of her mother, Mary Priscilla Smith, are comprised of writings and printed material.
Photographs are of people, artwork, and miscellaneous subjects. People represented are Russell and Mary Priscilla Smith, their children Xanthus and Mary Smith, and several other relatives including Xanthus's wife and Russell's sister, granddaughter, and uncle. Photographs include ambrotypes, daguerreotypes, and tintypes, along with glass negatives and a small number of original prints. Copy prints have been produced from the glass negatives and other cased photographs. Photographs of artwork are of paintings by Russell Smith, Xanthus Smith, and other artists.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms.
Subjects-Topical:
Painting, Modern--19th century--Pensylvania; Landscape painting; Women painters--Pennsylvania; Illustrators--Pennsylvania; Poets--Pennsylvania; Educators--Pennsylvania
Types of Materials:
Sketches; Sketchbooks; Works of art; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Daguerreotypes; Ambrotypes; Tintypes; Writings; Drawings
Names:
Smith, Mary Russell, 1842-1878; Smith, Russell, 1812-1896; Smith, Xanthus, 1839-1929; Smith, Mary Priscilla, 1819-1874
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Smith Family Papers, 1793-1977 (Box 1; 0.9 linear ft.)
Series 2: Russell Smith Papers, 1805-1954 (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear ft.)
Series 3: Xanthus Smith Papers, 1850-1953 (Boxes 3-4; 1.9 linear ft.)
Series 4: Mary Smith Papers, 1852-1877 (Box 5; 4 folders)
Series 5: Mary Priscilla Smith Papers, 1839-1874 (21 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1845-1934 (Box 6, Black Cabinet; 0.4 linear ft.)
Microfilm reel numbers and frames are referenced at folder headings in parenthesis when known.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Smith Family Papers, 1793-1977, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  The series is arranged as 4 subseries:
  1.1: Correspondence, 1828-1938
  1.2: Writings, 1852-1861
  1.3: Printed Material, 1793-1977
  1.4: Miscellaneous Items, 1826-1906
  - Correspondence, 1828-1938, 1.1:
    Family correspondence is both personal and professional in nature and the bulk of the material consists of letters to and from Russell Smith and Xanthus Smith. Correspondents include family, friends, colleagues, and arts organizations. Represented to a much lesser extent are Mary Smith and Mary Priscilla Smith, along with Russell Smith's niece, uncle and a few other relatives.
    - Family Correspondence, 1828-1938, (14 folders; Reel 2035: 2-1324; Reel 2036: 5-160) (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
  - Writings, 1852-1861, 1.2:
    Writings relate either to the entire Smith family or a variety of individuals. Notebooks are of University of Pennsylvania mathematics coursework. For additional writings see series for individual members of the Smith family.
    - Lists and Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Notebooks of [Uncle] Philip Conred (sic) Kunckle, undated, (2 volumes; Reel 2040: 698-807) (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Writings of Russell, Xanthus, and Mary Priscilla Smith, 1852-1861, (1 volume; Reel 2040: 454-537) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Printed Material, 1793-1977, 1.3:
    Printed material relates either to the entire Smith family or multiple individuals. For additional printed material see series for individual members of the Smith family.
    - Clippings and Articles (Box 1)
      - Smith Family, 1943-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Various Topics, 1793-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Publications, 1847-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Papers Read at a Reunion of McGaw Normal Institute...A Memorial to the Life, Work, and Character of Professor William Russell... (ancestor of Russell Smith), 1885 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1826-1906, 1.4:
    Miscellaneous items refer either to the entire Smith family or a variety of individuals including Horace Binder, father-in-law of Xanthus Smith. Records include financial records, printed material and memorabilia of Russell Smith, Mary Priscilla Smith and Xanthus Smith, in addition to genealogical notes and printing plates for Binder and Son business cards and an advertisement.
    - Financial Records, Printed Material and Memorabilia, 1826-1876, (Reel 2040: 668-697) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Horace Binder (Box 1)
      - Genealogical Notes, Correspondence, and Printed Material, 1894-1906, undated, (Reel 2040: 808-852) (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Printing Plates (Binder and Son business cards and advertisement; announcement of daughter's marriage to Xanthus Smith), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Russell Smith Papers, 1805-1954, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear ft.)
  This series is arranged as 5 subseries:
  2.1: Biographical Material, 1805-1879
  2.2: Writings, 1844-1906
  2.3: Artwork, 1834-1852
  2.4: Financial Records, 1832-1897
  2.5: Printed Material, 1833-1954
  - Biographical Material, 1805-1879, 2.1:
    Biographical material includes passports, a hymnal containing genealogical notes, and membership certificates. Also included are the marriage certificates of Russell Smith's parents, of Russell Smith and Mary Priscilla Smith, and of Xanthus Smith and Mary Binder. Centennial exhibition passes include photographs of Russell Smith and Mary Priscilla Smith.
    - Biographical and Genealogical Notes, 1805-1879, undated, (Reel 2036: 190-209) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Memorabilia, "Hair at fifty";" Centennial Exhibition Passes, 1862, 1877, (Reel 2037: 910-916) (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Personal Documents, 1805-1879, undated, (Reel 2036: 161-189) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Writings, 1844-1906, 2.2:
    Russell Smith's writings include an autobiography (with a version edited and completed by Xanthus Smith), and transcripts of correspondence, poems, and notes. For additional writings of Russell, Xanthus, and Mary Priscilla Smith see 1.2: Writings.
    - Autobiographical Writings (Box 2)
      - Volumes 1-3, circa 1880, circa 1884, (2 folders; Reel 2036: 685-847) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Manuscript 1 (holograph), "Autobiographical Recollections of Russell Smith" with additions by Xanthus Smith, circa 1884, (Reel 2036: 954-1037) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Manuscript 2 (typescript), "Autobiographical Recollections of Russell Smith" with conclusion by Xanthus Smith, circa 1884, (Reel 2036: 848-953) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 2)
      - Volumes 1-3, 1844-1851, undated, (Reel 2036: 1176-1246; Reels 2037: 7-109) (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Volumes 4-5, 1851-1852, (Volume 5 available on microfilm only; Reel 2037: 110-184) (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Volumes 6-7, 1852-1853, (Reel 2037: 185-323) (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Volume 8, 1879-1881, undated, (Reel 2037: 324-370) (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Volume 9, 1890-1896, (Reel 2037: 371-385) (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous Writings, Fragments, Notes, 1836-1839, undated, (Reel 2036: 1038-1074) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Notebooks 1 and 2, 1883-1890, (Reel 2036: 570-684) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Writings and Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Wilmington Opera House, Letters (photocopies) and Clippings, 1871-1873, undated, (Reel 2036: 210-237) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Volume 1 (includes copies of a few letters by Mary Smith), 1851, (Reel 2036: 238-375) (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Volume 2 (Russell Smith's letters, transcribed by Xanthus Smith, and copies of Xanthus Smith's letters), 1873-1906, (Reel 2036: 376-404) (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Volume 3, 1844-1891, (Reel 2036: 405-569) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Artwork, 1834-1852, 2.3:
    Artwork consists of sketch books with notes on France and loose pages with sketches and drawings in pencil, ink and watercolor. Filed with the artwork are printed reproductions of works by Russell Smith and a book of poems with reproductions of cast drawings titled Gems of Modern Sculpture.
    - Sketchbooks, Volumes 1-2, 1837-1852, undated, (Reel 2037: 288-641) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Sketches, 1834-1852, undated, (2 folders; Reel 2037: 288-641) (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Financial Records, 1832-1897, 2.4:
    Financial records consist of a series of cash books recording professional and personal expenses, and receipts and memorabilia from the family's 1851-1852 travels in Europe. Additional cash books can be found in 3.4: Xanthus Smith Papers, Financial Records.
    - Cash Books (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Volumes 1-3, 1832-1865, (Reel 2037: 917-1025) (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Volumes 4-5, 8, 1865-1887, (Reel 2037: 1026-1203, 1338-1378) (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Volumes 9-10 (entries for 1894-1897 recorded by Xanthus Smith), 1875-1897, (Reel 2037: 1379-1501, 1516-1535; Reel 2038: 5-55) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Investments, 1890-1893, (Reel 2037: 56-157) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1850s-1890, undated, (Reel 2038: 158-213) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Receipt for Medical Attendance, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Receipts and Memorabilia from European Trip, 1851-1852, (Reel 2038: 56-125) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Printed Material, 1833-1954, 2.5:
    This subseries consists of loose clippings and a scrapbook of clippings from Philadelphia newspapers, as well as a small number of exhibition catalogs.
    - Clippings, 1866-1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Clippings and Articles, 1856-1954, undated, (3 folders; Reel 2037: 703-909) (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, Labels, Prospectus, 1895-1948, undated, (Reel 2037: 684-702) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Scrapbook of Clippings from Philadelphia Newspapers mentioning Russell Smith, 1833-1857, (1 volume; Reel 2037: 642-683) (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Xanthus Smith Papers, 1850-1953, Series 3:; (Boxes 3-4; 1.9 linear feet)
  3.1: Biographical Information, 1856-1930
  3.2: Writings, 1850-circa 1921
  3.3: Artwork, 1852-1922
  3.4: Financial Records, 1864-1897
  3.5: Printed Material, 1860s-1953
  - Biographical Information, 1856-1930, 3.1:
    - Personal Documents, 1856-1930, (Reel 2038: 216-224) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writings, 1850-circa 1921, 3.2:
    Writings include Xanthus Smith's unpublished autobiography, the biographies of his father and sister, impressions of the Centennial art exhibition, journals, notes, and poems.
    For additional writings of Russell, Xanthus and Mary Priscilla Smith see 1.2: Smith Family Papers, Writings. See also 2.2: Russell Smith Papers, Writings, for Russell Smith's letters, transcribed by Xanthus Smith, and copies of Xanthus Smith's letters.
    - Autobiography, "An Unvarnished Tale" (Box 3)
      - First Draft, undated, (11 tablets in 4 folders; Reel 2038: 304-924) (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
      - Second Draft, undated, (12 tablets in 4 folders; Reel 2038: 925-1557; Reel 2039: 6-74) (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
      - Manuscripts, circa 1920, (3 folders; Reel 2039: 75-533) (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
    - "Biographical Sketch of Russell Smith by his Son Xanthus," undated, (Reel 2039: 591-618) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Biography of Russell Smith, undated, (Reel 2039: 619-663) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Contains biographical sketch of Russell Smith by X. S., also account of finding Revolutionary soldiers' graves on his place and then placing monumental stone on the spot," undated, (Reel 2039: 679-728) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "A Brief Sketch of the Life of Mary Smith, the Painter," 1878, (Reel 2039: 534-590) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Centennial Art Exhibition Impressions, 1876, (Reel 2040: 19-105) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Writings, undated, (Reel 2039: 667-678, 699-761) (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Volumes 1-2, circa 1851, (Reel 2039: 762-832) (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Volumes 3-4a and 4b, 1850-1851, (Reel 2039: 833-886) (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Volume 5, European Trip, 1851-1852, (2 folders; Reel 2039: 887-1048) (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
      - Volume 6, undated, (Reel 2039: 1049-1075) (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Volume 7, Journal, U.S.S. Wabash, Port Royal, S. C.; Volume 8, Dimensions of Wabash; Volume 9, "Chemistry Lectures Delivered by Prof. Rogers," 1862-1863, (Reel 2039: 1076-1190) (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Volumes 10-12, Journals, 1869-1872, (Reel 2039: 1191-1345) (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Volumes 13, 1862, undated, (Reel 2039: 1346-1389; Reel 2040: 7-18) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Notes about Russell Smith with Transcripts of Letters (for biography of his father?), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Notes and Writings, 1852-circa 1921, (2 volumes and loose items; Reel 2040: 106-236) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - "Pictures Painted since 1875 - Record of Frames 1881-2," undated, (Reel 2037: 1509-1515) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Scientific Notes, Poems, List of Paintings, 1852-1882, (Reel 2038: 225-302) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Speech Delivered at Women's School of Design, undated, (Reel 2040: 224-238) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Artwork, 1852-1922, 3.3:
    - Sketchbooks, 1852-1922, undated, (Reel 2040: 239-369) (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Sketches and "Classified List of War Sketches," 1879, undated, (Reel 2040: 239-369) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Financial Records, 1864-1897, 3.4:
    For additional cash books see 2.4: Russell Smith Papers, Financial Records.
    - Cash Books (Box 4)
      - Volumes 6-7, 1864-1870, undated, (Reel 2037: 1204-1337) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Printed Material, 1860s-1953, 3.5:
    - Clippings, Articles, Centennial Exhibition Passes with Photographs of Xanthus Smith, 1860s-1939, undated, (Reel 2040: 408-435) (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Clippings, Articles, Miscellaneous Publications, 1862-1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Clippings mentioning Mary Bender (Mrs. Xanthus) Smith, 1882, 1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1936, (Reel 2040: 370-386) (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Report of the Secretary of the Navy with an Appendix containing Reports from Officers; Webster's Army and Navy Pocket Dictionary, 1862-1863 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "Scrapbook started by Xanthus Smith when on board the U.S.S. Augusta and continued subsequent to the war, 1864-1870," 1864-1870, (Reel 2040: 387-407) (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Mary Smith Papers, 1852-1877, Series 4:; (Box 5; 4 folders)
  - List of Works, 1858-1877, (Reel 2040: 601-613) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 1)
  - Obituaries, 1878 (Box 5 (pam), Folder 2)
  - Sketches, 1852, undated, (Reel 2040: 614-620) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 3)
  - Writings, 1861, undated, (Reel 2040: 574-600) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 4)
- Mary Priscilla Smith Papers, 1839-1874, Series 5:; (Box 5; 2 folders)
  Writings include poems, a chronology and notes. For additional writings of Russell, Xanthus and Mary Priscilla Smith see 1.2: Smith Family Papers, Writings.
  - Printed Material, "The Indian Maid" in The Gentleman's Magazine (Mary Priscilla Smith, translator) and Death Notice, 1838, 1874 (Box 5 (pam), Folder 5)
  - Writings, Bound Volume, 1839, undated, (1 volume; Reel 2040: 621-667) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 6)
- Photographs, circa 1845-1934, Series 6:; (Box 6 and Black Cabinet; 0.4 linear ft.)